Boker tov בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Today's daf דף daf is good
motzei מוצאי motzei Shushan Purim שושן פורים. Shushan Purim. Today's daf דף
daf is kuf mem vav קמ"ו kuf mem vav 146 and we
start with a new mishnah משנה. mishnah. Each one of these mishnayot
משניות mishnayot is really about something significantly different. They're all dealing
with food-related issues but no categorization based on the melachah מלאכה. melachah.
So the first mishnah משנה mishnah just to remind us about the
barrel was about if a barrel breaks, mopping it up, concerns about
s'chitah סחיטה, s'chitah, but then all issues about squeezing foods. You've got
moraniyot מורניות moraniyot to squeeze vegetables. The next mishnah משנה mishnah was
about reheating food, putting food into hot water to reheat it, basically
a bishul achar bishul בישול אחר בישול bishul achar bishul concern, how
easily some things might cook more easily than others. And now we
turn to our mishnah משנה, mishnah, which is one of the big
questions on Shabbos שבת, Shabbos, which is really the source, well, our
contemporary application of it is opening packages. So let's take a look.
This is really the sugya סוגיא sugya on that. Let's take a
look at it. Mishnah משנה mishnah says as follows: Shover adam שובר
אדם shover adam kuf mem vav amud aleph קמ"ו עמוד א' kuf
mem vav amud aleph about ten lines down. Shover adam es hachavis
שובר אדם את החבית shover adam es hachavis leachol heimena grogrot לאכול
הימנה גרוגרות leachol heimena grogrot uval shelo yis'kavein la'asos k'li ובלבד שלא
יתכוין לעשות כלי. uval shelo yis'kavein la'asos k'li. So a person can
break a barrel which is stopped up, it's sealed, in order to
eat from it the pressed dates as long as he does not
intend to make a vessel out of it. So basically he can
cut off, break the top of the barrel, interesting why he would
bother doing that rather than just removing the seal, but he can
break off the top of the barrel in order to get to
the dates, but he's not trying to make a vessel. So
a rough analogy to that would be you could destroy the packaging
of something to get to what's inside, right, as long as you're
not trying to make a vessel out of it. Now what exactly
constitutes making a vessel will be an interesting question. Just to give
you something to think about, when you open up your milk carton,
although now they always have the plastic, they don't have those paper
ones anymore as much, but anyway, when you used to open up
your milk carton, or here's another example: when you open up your
bag of potato chips, is that making it a vessel because it's
now got a nice little opening on the top or you're just
trying to get into it and get access to the food? At
what stage is it considered making a vessel? So that's always the
key question.
Does it matter if it's reusable or something?
Right, so yes, so the Gemara גמרא Gemara doesn't talk about those
questions. For contemporary application, the question about reusability or theoretical reusability,
but the fact that in practice people throw it out, you know,
let's say a tuna fish can might be theoretically more useful than,
I don't know what exactly people would use it for anyway, than
a potato chip bag, but still the question is in practice it's
not made for that, it's made to be disposed of. So the
fact that things nowadays are disposable makes them significantly different than the
Gemara גמרא. Gemara. That's not in the direct context of the Gemara
גמרא. Gemara. Charlie, yes.
So but a barrel before you put the top on it was
clearly a vessel. Yes. And similarly a soda can before it had
the aluminum seal on the top was a vessel.
Right. The question about the soda can and about opening the top
is less about making the soda can a vessel, making the top
a vessel, making the screw top because before you broke off the
ring it could not be used for putting on and off of
cans. Now that you broke the ring it has a new functionality.
But the actual can can't be, you just break that thing off
then.
Right,
right. Although a can was, but a can also never had the
opening first.
Correct.
They have the top first,
wait, a soda can,
right, is. Oh, and then they put a top on.
Yeah, that's right.
They're sealed, they put a top on,
they're made from two pieces.
Okay, it's interesting, right,
so it needs to be in the pull-cap at least.
Alright, so anyway all of those are interesting questions as what degree
you say was already a vessel. I mean, you know, this barrel
was also a vessel and then it got stopped up and you
still can't make an opening in it that somehow is making it
a vessel as well. Yes.
What about making it, the potato chip bag, once you open it
it becomes a vessel to pour, then you can close it and
the next day you might open it, aren't you making it?
That's the question. You twist it up.
Right, how much does, so that's the question. Does it have to
be defined as a vessel for other things or if you're just
waiting to get out all of the contents you haven't really made
it a vessel, you're just getting to the contents but you don't
want them all at once? Basically the way that the most, I'm
not going to talk more halachah l'ma'aseh הלכה למעשה halachah l'ma'aseh now,
we'll look at the Gemara גמרא, Gemara, but I wanted to get
you thinking, but like the case that's most obvious is you rip
open the bag in a way that it totally destroys it and
all of it spills out. So it's no longer, it can't be
reused, it's no longer containing anything. Okay, anyway so that's our mishnah
משנה. mishnah. Okay, so you can break the barrel to get to
the food inside of it, but you cannot try, the breaking is
not somehow making it a vessel, not exactly clear what that constitutes.
V'ein nokvin megufah shel chavis ואין נוקבין מגופה של חבית. v'ein nokvin
megufah shel chavis. You can also not make a hole in the
stopper of a barrel. Now I have to tell you the cork,
right, I have to tell you here that Steinsaltz's picture was extremely
helpful because I was thinking about like a wine barrel that had
like just a flat circle top and what does it mean exactly?
But basically it's more like a... You think about like a jug
of wine that's got a nice cork in the top of it.
You think about like a jug of wine that's got a cork
on the side. Like let's imagine this whole thing is the cork
in the top of the jug of wine. So you would make
a hole in the cork rather than removing the cork or you
might want to make a hole in the side of the cork.
Okay, but it's a big it's a big cork on top into
the jug of wine. So you cannot make a hole because that
somehow would be like making a vessel.
So that would be a problem.
You cork up your cork? What?
And how would you cork up your cork? Yeah, that's the problem.
Well, but no, it could be very nice usable, meaning it's like
what do you mean how would you cork it up? I mean
some air would get in.
Yeah, no, meaning at some point you know you'd want to, I
would think in order for it to be a vessel it's got
to be functional afterwards.
It is functional, it's just that it's letting air into the wine
bottle. Anyway, I don't know, yeah, I don't know. So anyway you
cannot make a hole in it, דברי רבי יהודה. divrei Rabbi Yehuda.
וחכמים מתירין, v'chachamim matirin, but look at this, the חכמים chachamim allow
it. So not exactly clear why it's okay to make a hole
in a cork and how that's less drastic than making the vessel
out of you know when you're getting into the barrel. So exactly
again what the lines are are not clear. Now, now we go
on. ולא יקבנה מצדה, v'lo yikevena mitzidah, you should not make a
hole on the side of it. The גמרא Gemara will discuss, does
that mean the side of the cork or the side of the
barrel? But presumably now we're back to the Rabbis' position, not רבי
יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. So that they do say is a problem. ואם
היתה נקובה, v'im hayta nekuva, now if it did have a hole
and here it answers Michael's questions what would you do to seal
that hole after it was made. לא יתן עליה שעווה, lo yiten
aleha sha'ava, do not put wax over the hole to seal it.
Okay, so don't do that on שבת Shabbat either. Now that's not
making a vessel, that's just sealing a hole, but why is that
a problem? מפני שהוא ממרח, mipnei shehu memare'ach,
that's another problem about smoothing. You aren't, which is a תולדה toldah
of ממחק. memachek. The same way you couldn't get off the hair
of a piece of leather to smooth the leather to make the
leather, you cannot take some material and smooth it out, smooth it
out and make it like a nice smooth surface. So this is
a big question about what constitutes smoothing. I'll just tell you here
also parenthetically, big issues about things like
Desitin and Neosporin and toothpaste, where there you've got something that is
somewhat you know thick, it's not like, it's not like you know,
something like they would put on by the way, you know they'd
put oil on their body. So basically on שבת, Shabbat, right, there's
no איסור issur of סיכה sichah on שבת. Shabbat. So I tell
people if something is basically the consistency of oil it's not an
issue at all. So you know it's like type of hand cream
lotion, it's no different than oil. But if you get the type
of like what's it called, the Vaseline, right, or the Desitin, which
is thick, so and then you smooth it, is that like the
smoothing of the wax? Or you know toothpaste? And the difference I
think there is or maybe it's not such a difference to me,
it's hard to imagine why it's a מלאכה melacha of smoothing if
you're not doing it to create a smooth surface. You're just trying
to apply it all over, you're just trying to get it on
the whole surface, but you're not trying to actually create some type
of a you know thing out of what you're smoothing.
Okay, that's the classic ממרח memare'ach like what...
well the classic ממחק memachek is the smoothing of the of the
skin of the leather. So that's actually to making then it a
nice skin. Okay, ממרח memare'ach is smoothing some material, this is one
of the classic applications in the משנה. Mishna. So here by the
wax, you know, by all those other things you're really just trying
to get it on. You're not trying to make you know, you
don't want the smooth surface to serve any function. Here, it's a
little bit different when you smooth over the wax on the opening
of a you know of a hole, you're not just trying to
you're getting it in all places, you want it to be a
certain way in order to stop up the hole effectively. So anyway,
but that is a very big issue about ממרח, memare'ach, and it's
usually applied pretty broadly למעשה, l'ma'aseh, you know. So there's
toothpaste not, there's a big there's a more lively debate about, but
things like yeah, but things like Desitin or
or Vaseline or whatever, the general approach is to be pretty מחמיר.
machmir.
Yeah, then it also get into problems of פסיק רישיה, p'sik reishah,
you saying Desitin's for רפואה? refuah?
Yeah, I'm not getting into there. If it's for a child, it's
all anyway חולה שאין בו סכנה. choleh she'ein bo sakanah. Okay, so
אמר רבי יהודה, amar Rabbi Yehuda, and now we're just to show
you what's at stake. אמר רבי יהודה, amar Rabbi Yehuda, מעשה בא
לפני רבן יוחנן בן זכאי בערב, ma'aseh bo lifnei Rabban Yochanan ben
Zakkai b'Arev, a place,
a story came to Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai in this place Arev
about somebody that smoothed wax over the hole of a barrel, ואמר
חוששני לו מחטאת. v'amar chosheshani lo mechatat. I'm afraid he might be
חייב חטאת chayav chatat or it would really be a דאורייתא. d'oraita.
Okay, so most of the משניות mishnayot we've been dealing with in
the last few פרקים prakim just say don't do this, don't do
this, don't do that, and don't tell you if it's rabbinic or
biblical and then the גמרא Gemara always asks what happens if you
do it? And somebody always says it's biblical, and sometimes there's a
response that well maybe not. Anyway, here it seems very clear. It
says ממרח, memare'ach, which is very clearly identifying it as a you
know as a classic forbidden category of labor and the actual line
at the end of ואמר חוששני לו מחטאת. v'amar chosheshani lo mechatat.
So a lot of extremely relevant things in this משנה. Mishna. Let's
take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. אמר רב הושעיא, amar Rav
Hoshaya, said Rav Hoshaya, לא שנו אלא דרוסות אבל מפורדות לא. lo
shanu ela drusot aval mefuradot lo.
Now coming at this from totally different perspective, something we wouldn't have
even thought was an issue. He's concerned about
taking the like the the
knife. separated, you can't. Now why does that matter? The issue's about
breaking the barrel. Why does it care whether the big—whether the stuff
in it is together or separate? So we're going to see the
reason is that he doesn't want you to pick up the knife
unless it is for a legitimate purpose, unless it's for its standard
purpose. Now remember, we normally say you don't—that doesn't matter, you can
even take a כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור kli she'melachto l'issur like a hammer
to crack nuts. But there's a position that says that you cannot
use any vessel except for its standard purpose. So only if you
could pick up the knife because you're going to use it to
cut, you know, the dates from one another, then once you have
a legitimate reason to have the knife, then you can use it
to break the barrel. Okay, so this is a total side concern
of מוקצה. muktzeh.
This is somebody else's position, though?
Rabbi Nechemia's position? Right, right, which the גמרא Gemara is going to
say. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, מיתיבי, Meitivei, I'll ask you
on this. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel אומר, omer,
says, מביא אדם חבית של יין, mevi adam chavit shel yayin, you
can take your barrel of wine, ומתיז ראשה בסייף, umatiz rosha besayif,
and use like a sword to chop off the head, ומניחה לפני
האורחים בשבת, uminicha lifnei ha'orchim be'Shabbat,
and put it in front of the guests on Shabbat. It would
sort of be like one of those performance, you know, meals, like
you know you go to a restaurant and they have like—they cook
the food in front of you. So it seems like it was
something dramatic. Like why are you bothering chopping the thing off? It
would seem like, you know, like that's maybe—we'll see that in a
minute that like if you make a big opening in it, it's
sort of like saying, here, it's for everybody to drink, I'm not
being stingy. So you take your sword, you cut off the top
of it. Okay, you can do that. ואינו חושש, Ve'eino choshesh, and
it—I'm sorry, and it's not a problem. So you see that you
can—that it says that it's wine. So wine is not like pressed,
you know, dates. You don't need a knife to cut wine. So
the גמרא Gemara says, ההוא רבנן, Hahu rabbanan, that's the rabbis who
don't care about using, you know, knives—you know, vessels for their non-standard
purpose. מתניתין רבי נחמיה היא, Matnitin Rabbi Nechemia hi, our משנה mishna
is Rabbi Nechemia
who says you can only use a knife or a sword for
its legitimate purpose, and therefore you need to first have a reason
to pick it up to break the food in the barrel, and
then you can use it to break the barrel. So the גמרא
Gemara says, ומאי דוחקיה דרבי הושעיא לאוקמי מתניתין כרבי נחמיה ובדרוסות? U'mai
duchkeia de'Rabbi Oshia le'ukmi matnitin ke'Rabbi Nechemia u'be'drusot? What—what pushed Rabbi Oshia,
forced him to say our משנה mishna was talking
according to Rabbi Nechemia and therefore only in cases when these are
pressed together? לוקמי במפורדות, Lokmi be'mefuradot, just say it's
talking even about separate, you know,
dates, ורבנן, ve'rabbanan, and it's the rabbis. Why did he introduce this
whole weird discussion in our, you know, in our משנה? mishna? אמר
רבא מתניתין קשיא ליה, Amar Rava matnitin kashya lei, Rava says he
was bothered by the משנה. mishna. מאי איריא דתני גרוגרות? Mai irya
detani grogrot?
Why did the משנה mishna start talking about, you know, pressed dates?
Why did it have to give that specific example? The fact that
sometimes the משנה mishna gives concrete examples—okay, but he thought why that
example? How about wine? Wine is more common and that's in the
ברייתא. braita. וליתני פירות, U'litni perot, talk about just fruit in general,
make it more generic. אלא שמע מינה בדרוסות, Ela shema mina be'drusot,
he digs this because these are things that are standardly pressed together.
Okay, fine. Anyway, that's a complete side issue about רבי נחמיה Rabbi
Nechemia and מוקצה. muktzeh. Now back to—well, not back to, because we're
going to have another ברייתא braita which is also going to be
on this, on this מוקצה muktzeh issue before we get back to
the heart of our משנה. mishna. So תני חדא, Tani chada, we
taught one ברייתא, braita, חותלות של גרוגרות, chotalot shel grogrot, if you
have basically wrappers, like these are types of wicker baskets that you
would put around these—these, you know, pressed dates, these dried out dates.
And you would do it in order to help them ripen. Like
you know they tell you now to put things in like a
brown bag. Okay, so they would wrap it up in these types
of—it would be like a wicker basket sealed that the stuff would
be in it and it would be there to ripen. And you
now want to open it up to get to the stuff inside
on Shabbat, but are you like destroying the basket? Well, this is
very similar to again like ripping up the packaging to get to
the food inside. Even though this is even more of a כלי,
kli, this is a real basket, but you're destroying it to get
to—but it is also in the process of destruction. So it says
like this, it says חותלות של גרוגרות ושל תמרים, chotalot shel grogrot
veshel tamarim, or of like not pressed dates, but just standard dates.
גרוגרות Grogrot are pressed dates, right? We're getting confused which are—grogrot are
dates or figs? Grogrot are figs. Pressed figs. I've been—I've been saying
dates the whole time. I'm having word dates. I know, but what
are גרוגרות, grogrot, which one are they? Pressed figs. All right, so
change everything I just said, I keep on getting it confused. All
right, fine. So it's—so it's pressed figs. So okay, now we have
to relearn the whole דף. daf. Okay, so anyway, it's pressed figs.
So okay, now you have them wrapping up these pressed figs. ושל
תמרים, Veshel tamarim, or dates. מתיר ומפקיע וחותך. Matir u'mafki'a ve'chotech. So
you can undo if the—if the—if the cover is knotted on, you
can undo the knot. רש"י Rashi in another גמרא Gemara says we're
talking about a קשר שאינו של קיימא, kesher she'eino shel kayama, it's
made for undoing, right? It's only there temporarily. And you can be
ומפקיע, mafki'a, you can actually like tear into, cut into the whole
basket, like rip up the basket. וחותך, Vechotech, or like also, you
know, or cut the—or cut the string that's holding on. Basically, you'd
have a cover, it would be knotted on with a string, so
you could either undo the string, cut the string, cut into the
basket, do whatever you want. Okay, so that's what you can do.
ותניא אידך, vesanya idach, but we have another ברייתא braisa that says
מתיר, matir, you can undo the string, אבל לא מפקיע, aval lo
mafkia, you can't cut into the basket, ולא חותך, velo choteich, and
you can't cut the string. So again, we might have wanted to
say it's a difference maybe, whether there's some type of a מלאכה
melacha involved in cutting, maybe it's, I don't know, סתירה בכלים stira
bicheilim or something? Anyway, the גמרא Gemara what's now, now, just says
what it's been saying before, לא קשיא, lo kashya, it's not difficult,
הא רבנן הא רבי נחמיה. ha rabanan ha Rabi Nechemya. This is
again the question of the rabbis and Rabbi Nechemya, whether you can
pick up that knife to cut the basket or to cut the
string for some other purpose. דתניא רבי נחמיה אומר, detanya Rabi Nechemya
omer, I mean, for such a purpose rather than its standard purpose.
Rabbi Nechemya says, אפילו תרביא ואפילו טליף ואפילו סכין, afilu tarvai va'afilu
talif va'afilu sakin, even if you have like various types of like
a, a certain type of a, of a shovel or a garment
or a, or a knife, אין ניטלין אלא לצורך תשמישן, ein nitlin
ela letzoirech tashmishan, you can only use them for their classical use.
And therefore the issue here, we're not even talking about the concern
about making vessels, it's just a מוקצה muktzah concern according to Rabbi
Nechemya. So I can't use my sword to do הטמנה hatmanah or
something, basically. Okay, so that's like a side issue, which we don't
פוסק pasken Rabbi Nechemya. Now, before we get onto the גמרא Gemara
about making a nice opening, I do want to say something about
destroying the packaging. Why is it מותר mutar if you completely destroy
the packaging? So if you look at רש"י Rashi in the משנה,
Mishnah, שובר אדם חבית, shover adam chavis, רש"י Rashi says way back
to the משנה, Mishnah, first רש"י Rashi on the משנה, Mishnah, he
says מלאה גרוגרות בסכין ובסייף לאכול הימנו גרוגרות שיוצאות שאין במקלקל שום
איסור בשבת. meleiah grogeros besakin uvessayif leechol heimenu grogeros sheyotzos she'ein bemekalkel
shum issur beShabbos. Doing something destructive has no prohibition on שבת. Shabbos.
Now, the question is like, really? I mean, isn't it at least
רבנן rabanan ribbinically forbidden? So the ר"ן Ran says okay, okay, it's
not a problem when it's done לצורך שבת. letzoirech Shabbos. Okay, well
that's also interesting, because that means that, you know, that you can,
מקלקל mekalkel would always be allowed as long as it's לצורך שבת.
letzoirech Shabbos. Even that seems a little bit more latitude than we
tend to give it. There's another point though to be made here
as well, which is מקלקל mekalkel is like still ribbinically problematic when
you're doing a מלאכה, melacha, but you're doing it in a מקלקל
mekalkel way. You know, so, I don't know, you light a fire
and it's destructive rather than helpful. So you did a מלאכה, melacha,
you made a fire, but it was מקלקל, mekalkel, it was destructive.
Okay. Here, what מלאכה melacha did you do? Is it obvious what
מלאכה melacha you do by destroying the barrel, by destroying packaging? Yes,
you are being מקלקל, mekalkel, but are you doing the מלאכה melacha
to begin with? So it might be ripping it. Oh, so מחתך.
mechateich. מחתך mechateich is only a problem when you do something like
to a very specific type of a size. Okay, which might mean
so maybe, but if you're just destroying, you're not cutting something to
a particular size. What about letters on it? Okay, well that would,
now you're talking contemporary and we could talk about that later, but
that's not the case in the גמרא, Gemara, in the משנה. Mishnah.
So the most you could be doing here would be סותר בכלים.
soser bicheilim. If there's בניין בכלים, binyan bicheilim, is there סותר בכלים?
soser bicheilim? Right? If you can constructively, does the מלאכה melacha of
בונה boneh apply to a vessel? So if you constructively, can you
also deconstructive-ly? But here's my question, and this is I think what
רש"י Rashi is getting at. I don't think רש"י Rashi is maybe
is saying מקלקל mekalkel is always מותר, mutar, but what I would
like to understand why it's really מותר mutar here, is do you
really call this סותר בכלים? soser bicheilim? Like if I go ahead
and I take something and I throw it in the fire, so
I'm doing a מלאכה melacha of הבערה, havarah, but am I doing
a מלאכה melacha of סותר? soser? סותר soser presumably is if I
like disassemble my vessel, right? If I just completely destroy. Now, it's
true by like a building, if I knock down a building in
order to build, that would be סותר, soser, a real סותר. soser.
But if we're talking about vessels, presumably סותר soser would be a
disassembling of it, not a just destructive destroying. Like something that's in
parts you unscrewed it. Exactly, you unscrewed it and you unscrewed it.
So anyway, it's an interesting question why even when you're not making
a vessel, why is this מותר? mutar? Is it מקלקל, mekalkel, מקלקל
לצורך שבת? mekalkel letzoirech Shabbos? I would and I would also throw
in the idea that it's questionable if there's a מלאכה melacha being
done here at all, it's just a completely destructive act. Okay, but
that's what is allowed. Now we're going to turn to the problematic
case, which is when you're making a nice opening. Yes. Well, my
question here is it says you can't use a knife except for
its designated use. Right. So but how else would you open that
basket of figs, wouldn't you use a knife? I mean... Well, no,
but a standard knife- knives are used. First of all you could
undo it. You could maybe if you have like a scissors, maybe
that would be okay. You know what I'm saying? But like a
normal knife here is being, is that's not the stand- you're going
the opposite. What would be the best thing to use for this
basket? But the question starts from the vessel,
not from what you have to get done. And the question is
what is the standard use of a knife? So and that's not
to-
that's to like cut food with, it's not to, now maybe certain
knives it is. Maybe your saw in from your tool box is
that the standard use of it. So you know, but okay then
that
might be an issue because it's a כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור kli shemelachto
le'issur and it's more standardly
used for more forbidden types of things on שבת. Shabbos. Okay, but
now we get to the more central relevant issue of making a
nice opening. So let's take a look. בעי מיניה מרב ששת, bei
minei meRav Sheshes, they asked רב ששת. Rav Sheshes. מהו למברז חביתא
בבורטיא בשבתא? mahu limvraz chavisa bevurtya beShabbasa? What's the story about puncturing
a barrel with a... He says it's like a spear, but it
might just be like an awl, you know, some type of a
vessel made for making a nice hole in the side of a
barrel in order to let out the wine. A corkscrew, but here,
it's not into—it's not just into a cork and it's just for
pulling out the cork; it's actually making the hole in the side
to make it that you can use it. Okay, so that really
would seem like that's like a classic making of a vessel; you're
creating a hole that now it's going to use it from. So
here's the question: לפתחא קא מכוין ואסור, Lipitcha ka mechavein ve'assur, are
you doing it to make an opening and therefore it's forbidden, okay,
or לעין יפה קא מכוין ושרי? Le'ayn yafa ka mechavein veshari? Maybe
you're just doing it so that it looks nice. What does that
mean? So רש"י Rashi says, רש"י Rashi claims that you're not using
like the classic type of a thing to open it with, that
you are using actually like a spear, not a designated כלי kli
to open it, and therefore he says, you know, if you really
were making the standard hole, you would have made it the normal
way, a nice circular hole with the right type of a vessel.
The fact that you're taking like a huge, you know, whatever it
is, like a huge knife and you're doing a stabbing in it,
that's just like this idea of cutting off the top of the
barrel, showing your guests how generous you are. Look, I'm going to
make a huge hole, you can take as much wine as you
want and so on, and it's to get the wine out but
not to make it as like a standard functional opening of the
barrel. See, that's the way רש"י Rashi explains the case. You normally
would take a—let's—this is the way רש"י Rashi understands it, a designated
type of a—of a—of a screw, of a—of an awl, okay, I
should have said awl in the first case because it's not the
way רש"י Rashi says it, to make—to make the hole that you
would use on the side of the barrel to take out the
wine. You didn't. You took this big spear off your wall and
you made a huge hole in the side. So maybe that's also
making it into a vessel just with a bigger hole, non-standard hole,
or maybe you're doing it because you just want to show how
generous you are and therefore you're not really making it—obviously you're trying
to get to the wine, but the question is: Are you making
it like that this is now part—a functional part of the vessel,
or is it just giving you access to the wine? Okay, so
that's the question. Again, and you can see why it's so hard
to—to apply—you know, to think about the packaging because some of these
distinctions are very hard to, you know, quantify. Okay, so let's see
what his answer is. אמר ליה, Amar lei, he said to him,
לפתחא קא מכוין ואסור. Lipitcha ka mechavein ve'assur. Nope, sorry, you're trying
to make an opening and it's forbidden. By the way, notice it
uses the word אסור. assur. רש"י Rashi keeps on talking about making
a vessel, you know, and so on like it's דאורייתא. de'oraysa. There
are some positions here that—that none of this is דאורייתא, de'oraysa, this
is all דרבנן. derabbanan. Okay, so that's another whole question; even if
you did it, what type of prohibition is this? So the only
problem when we mentioned חטאת chatas was—was the ממרח. memarei'ach. Right. מיתיבי,
Meisivei, I'll ask you on this: רבן גמליאל אומר, Rabban Gamliel omer,
מביא אדם חבית של יין ומתיז ראשה בסייף, Meivi adam chavit shel
yayin umatiz roshah besayif, the cutting off the top with a sword.
That's what we said before. So, משום דהתם ודאי לעין יפה קא
מכוין, Mishum dehasam vaday le'ayn yafa ka mechavein, there clearly he's not
really trying to make it as a functional spout of the barrel;
he's just trying to, you know, and make the big hole but
to show everybody how generous he is. And again, you know, you
can get ac—you need to break the thing to get access, but
that doesn't mean you're making it as like a functional opening of
the barrel. הכא אי איתא דלעין יפה קא מכוין, Hacha ei issa
de'le'ayn yafa ka mechavein, here if you were trying to just show
your generosity, לפתחיה מיפתח, Liphthachay miphtach, then just do like that, cut
off the top or open up the top of it. But you're
not opening up the top; you're making a hole on the side
and therefore even if it's not with like a standard hole, we
consider that to be a type of a, you know, of—of adding
a functionality and making this into a vessel. Okay, so that's that.
Now we continue. אין נוקבין מגופה, Ein nokvin megupa, then the משנה
Mishnah goes on to say, don't make a hole in the—in it
according to רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, the top of it, the seal,
the cork we said, but—but the חכמים Chachamim allow it. And then
it says but don't make it on the side. So אמר רב
הונא, Amar Rav Huna, מחלוקת למעלה, Machlokes lemala, the issue is on
the top of the cork, like you know where you would put
a corkscrew; so you're making a hole through the top of the
cork so that you can pour wine. It's like a wine jug
with a cork and the hole is through the top, goes all
the way down so you can now pour wine out of the
hole in the top of the cork. That's where they debate, because
that's not a normal type of an opening and therefore the חכמים
Chachamim say it's okay. אבל מן הצד, Aval min hatzad, on the
side of the cork, דברי הכל אסור. Divrei hakol assur. If this
were the cork, right? So rather than doing it here on the
top, if the cork is here in my—in my wine jug, you
make the hole on the side. That's much more of a usable
thing because if it's on the top, right, dirt gets in and
all this type of stuff gets in, it's not a normal way
in which people make an opening, but to make a hole on
the side and then to pour from that hole, that might be
normal enough and therefore the חכמים Chachamim would—would say it is a
problem. והיינו דקתני, Vehaynu de'katni, and that's why the משנה Mishnah says,
לא יקבנה מצדה, Lo yikvena mitzidah, don't do it on the side,
that's going according to חכמים, Chachamim, and it means even the side
of the cork is a problem—going, right, even the חכמים—and Chachamim it's
even the side—the side of the cork is a problem. רב חסדא
אמר, Rav Chisda amar, and now רב חסדא Rav Chisda says, מחלוקת
מן הצד, Machlokes min hatzad, the problem is—no, that if it's on
the top of the cork, everybody says that's fine. fine, that's certainly
not a normal opening. The question is the side of the cork.
There, you know, Rabbi Yehuda says no and the Rabbis say yes.
אבל על גבה אבל מחלוקת מן הצד, Aval al gabah aval machlokes
min hatzad, so the debate is the side of the cork. אבל
על גבה, Aval al gabah, the top of the cork דברי הכל
מותר, divrei hakol mutar, everybody says okay. והא דתניא לא יקבנה מצדה,
Vehade d'tanya lo yikvena mitziddah, so what does it mean don't make
it on the side, which sounds like that's the Rabbis if they
say it's okay to make it on the side of the cork?
התם בגופא דחבית, Hatam begufa dechavit, that's the side of the actual
jug itself. That's changing the actual jug as opposed to making the
hole in it. So again, what we have here is certain types
of holes are allowed: a hole on the top is allowed, that's
not standard; a hole on the side of the cork might be
allowed, maybe that's also not the standard way; maybe also it's not
really making a vessel. Maybe the real vessel here, it's sort of
like the question about, you know, we discussed before, the bottle top.
Do you really talk about making the bottle top into a vessel?
You know, so if you're making only a hole in the cork,
are you really making a vessel there? Maybe it's only a problem
when you make a hole in the side of the barrel. That's
really maybe the A more standard way maybe, and B maybe the
really more concern of making a vessel. But I understand, is making
a hole on the side, is it the same thing as topping
off the top of it? No, if you wanted to make it
into a vessel, what you'd do is you'd just take off the
cork, why would you be puncturing your barrel? Yeah, that I don't
get, I really don't get that, you're right. I know, it doesn't
make any sense. Why would any of this be normal? Who makes
a hole in the side of the barrel? Maybe to make a
spout? Right, but why would you make a spout rather than just
remove the cork? I don't know. Right, that's why I thought we
were talking less about a jug, again I was sort of following
Steinsaltz because he makes it understandable, but I guess you could imagine
a huge barrel that also has like a thick raised top, so
that it could both be on the top and the side of
the thing. If you're talking about a huge barrel, then you understand
why you don't just remove it and pour it, why you make
a hole in the side. So you are right, it is easier
to understand if, and that's, you know, look, it's like the famous
משנה Mishna in the third פרק Perek of עבודה זרה: Avodah Zarah:
היינו כד היינו חבית, hainu kad hainu chavit, right? A חבית chavit
normally is like a barrel, and a כד kad is like a
jug, and sometimes they're used interchangeably. So if it's talking about a
barrel, it does make a lot more sense why you would not
standardly just make a hole on the, you know, remove the cork,
but you'd make a hole in the side. Yeah, and then I'm
along the same question, isn't it already a vessel? Right, so that's
the question. It is, so is changing the configuration... now again, if
it's, let's assume again, you know, I do think that understanding this
as a barrel makes more sense. I've been saying jug because, you
know, because that picture helped me understand why there's thickness to the
top, but a barrel makes a lot more sense. Because a barrel,
it might be a vessel, and this is exactly the issue about
like opening cans or opening packaging. It's a vessel to contain the
wine, but it's not yet a vessel to sort of distribute the
wine, you know? Because there's no way now to effectively use it
to get the wine out. So it's the same type of an
idea.
You've got like a can and you, you know, make a hole
in it or whatever, you're changing its functionality from only a storage
vessel to a serving vessel.
So that's I really think what's going on here. And again, that
why it all makes much more sense assuming we're talking about a
barrel and not a jug. Okay? Yes, it said מהו למיברז בחצבא.
mahu limivraz bachatzva. ברז Barez in Hebrew means spigot. Aha, right, that's
why I think that's what... right, that's a good point, and we're
going actually see that in a minute. Right now we're just talking
about the hole, when we turn the דף, daf, we're going to
talk about putting in actually like a pipe and using it as
a faucet, as a spigot. So that's exactly where we're going. Right.
Okay. So now fine. So revise all of that, we're talking about,
it does make a lot more sense, which is how I always
thought until I looked at Steinsaltz's side, that we're talking about a
barrel. And okay, and that's the issue. So the classic thing would
be let's say to put it in the side, and then you're
of the barrel, and then you're really changing the configuration of the
barrel. And as Seth said, then you obviously could put in a
spigot. And the question is, is it even a problem if it's
on the seal, on the top, the top of the seal, the
side of the seal? Okay. So now the Gemara continues. Okay. תנו
רבנן, Tanu rabbanan, our rabbis taught: אין נוקבין נקב חדש בשבת, ein
nofkin nekiv chadash beShabbat, you cannot make a new hole on Shabbat,
so that seems to be what we've been saying. ואם בא להוסיף
מוסיף, Ve-im ba lehosif, mosif, but if you want to and you
had an existing hole, you can expand it. That's sort of like,
you know, what Paul was saying, then you're not really doing something
new, it already existed, you're just making it bigger. ויש אומרים אין
מוסיף, Veyesh omrim ein mosif, and some say you can't even make
the hole bigger. ושוין שנוקבין נקב ישן לכתחילה, Veshavin shenokvin nekiv yashan
l'chatchila, and what everybody agrees is if you have an old hole
that's been sealed up, let's say with the wax as we read
in the beginning in the משנה, Mishna, then you can remove the
wax and pierce it. So there's the idea, right? That if the
thing already exists, then just, you know, removing the current cover, and
that's the whole issue they say now about these soda bottles, right?
Is that the whole thing, you know, the cap actually gets put,
you know, it exists with its opening before and then you just
put the cap on afterwards, so removing the cap... is not making
the bottle into a new vessel. Whether it's making the cap into
a vessel is a different story. Anyway, okay. ותנן u-tnan שנתקבה she-nitkevah
כביצה ke-veitzah בתוך be-toch הקב ha-kav מאי שנא מנקב חדש דלא? mai
shna mi-nekev chadash de-lo? Why the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma who says
you can't make a new hole, why not? דקא מתקן פתחא de-ka
mataken pitcha because you are making a hole, an opening, you are
fixing an opening, is literally what it means. הוספה נמי קא מתקן
פתחא hosefa nami ka mataken pitcha when you add to it, you're
also fixing an opening. Now again, what is very interesting about the
next discussion is that the גמרא Gemara has a heightened focus on
the idea that it's an opening. Meaning our focus would be, who
cares what you're doing? Opening this, that. The point is you're making
it into a functional vessel, you're adding functionality, you're changing it. But
the גמרא Gemara has a heightened focus on that the problem is
a hole. And a hole, making holes are a particular type of
בונה. boneh. One way you do בונה boneh is you make holes
in things. Right? You make a hole in the wall and you're
going to put in the window. You make a hole to, I
don't know, to insert into a peg. So making a hole, not
looking at it sort of macro that you're making a vessel, but
looking at it micro, you're making a hole, that's the problem. So
if that's the problem, even if it's already functional, making a bigger
hole should be a problem. You see the difference? If it's about
the functionality, you understand the difference between why a bigger hole shouldn't
be an issue, it's already functional. But if the problem is not
making the object, the vessel, but making a hole, so you could
say, so making a bigger hole, the act of making a hole
is itself problematic. So making a bigger hole should also be problematic.
So the גמרא Gemara says, so אמר רבא, Amar Rava, here's the
story. דבר תורה Devar Torah biblically, כל פתחא דלא עביד לאכנוסי ולאפוקי
לאו פתחא הוא. kol pitcha delo avid le-achnosi u-le-apoki lav pitcha hu.
Any hole that's made, this is a type of like a בונה
boneh issue, that's not made for things going in and out, two-directional,
is not considered an opening to be a מלאכה melacha on שבת.
Shabbat. ורבנן הוא דגזרו משום לול של תרנגולים. ve-Rabbanan hu de-gazru mishum
lul shel tarnegolim. But the Rabbis say, don't even make a one-directional
hole, because you'll come to make a two-directional, because we have a
case of a two-directional that seems to be not so clear and
people will confuse it. What's that case? It's the case of a
chicken coop. דעביד לעולי לאוירא da-avid le-ulei le-avira that you make the
hole in the chicken coop to bring air in, ולאפוקי הבלא u-le-apoki
hevla to bring the bad air out. Okay? So the window in
the chicken coop is done for things going in both directions. But
maybe it's not so obvious that's what's done. So if we let
you make a one-directional hole, you'll come to make, you'll confuse it,
and you'll think, 'Oh, I can make it in the chicken coop,'
and it'll lead to making like two-directional holes and that's the problem.
So all of a sudden we stop talking about making vessels and
we become this hyper-micro focus on making holes. And one very particular
type of a hole is a problem: two-directional. And rabbinically you can't
even make one-directional. And this hole for the wine barrel is primarily
one-directional, to get the wine out. And therefore it should not be
a biblical problem. It's only a rabbinic problem. So that's the debate
now about adding to this hole. So let's take a look. So
אמר רבא, Amar Rava, so therefore... is the debate is this building
or just even with the barrel? No, with the barrel. Okay. Could
you use a hole in a barrel for building? Well, לול של
תרנגולים lul shel tarnegolim might not be a... might be more of
a portable type of a thing, although it is more building-like, but
it might not be מחובר. mechubar. I understand why the whole thing
is very strange, this hyper-focus on the holes. ואם בא להוסיף מוסיף.
ve-im ba lehosif mosif. So now I'm going to say that if
you want to add, you can add. Why? At least according to
תנא קמא. Tanna Kamma. אוסופי ודאי בלול של תרנגולים לא אתי לאוסופי.
osufi vadai be-lul shel tarnegolim lo atei le-osufi. Now it gets even
stranger. Because nobody would ever make a bigger hole in the chicken
coop. Like the only one hole we might make, if you let
me make this hole, the only one problematic hole I could come
to make is the chicken coop, no other thing I'll ever do.
Okay? And therefore we don't have to be afraid I'll make a
bigger hole on a chicken coop. Why don't you make a bigger
hole on a chicken coop? משום ריחשא, mishum richsha, because you don't
want the weasels and the other animals to get into your chicken
coop. So it's so bizarre, right? Don't make certain types of holes
not because you'll make generically problematic two-directional. No, because of a very
specific concern of chicken coops.
And therefore since adding will not be a concern there, there's not
a גזירה gezeira of adding. Anyway, this becomes what complicates the whole
discussion about packaging.
Is packaging the idea of making, you know, the milk carton into
a vessel, or is packaging somehow the only problem is making a
hole? And then it gets to narrow definitions of what types of
holes are problematic, and biblically only two-directional, rabbinically even one-directional. So it's
a complete like shift of focus. Okay. ויש אומרים אין מוסיפין. ve-yesh
omrim ein mosifin. And some say no, you can't even add to
the hole in this wine barrel. Why? זימנין דלא תקנה מעיקרא. zimnin
delo taknah mei-ikara. Because sometimes even in your chicken coop you would
not have made the opening the right way to begin with. ואתי
לארווחי בה ve-atei le-arvuchei bah and you'll come to expand it. So
it is relevant for the גזירה gezeira of chicken coops. רב נחמן
משמיה דיוחנן אמר הלכה כויש אומרים. Rav Nachman mishmeih d'Yochanan amar halacha
ke-yesh omrim. We rule like ויש אומרים yesh omrim that you can't
even add to the hole. Okay. So now we have this issue
about making the hole on the side, which we all thought was
an issue about making it into a vessel, and now we see
that we are talking about that one way to focus on it
is a specific problem of making holes.
You say so both, right? It could be both, but if there
was both we wouldn't have said that it would be allowed.
We would have focused more on maybe some might say both issues.
What? Maybe. Just have to think about that could be. Okay. ושלבין
שנקב נקבו ישן לכתחילה V'shalvin she'nakav nikvu yashen l'chatchila continuing in this
בריתא, Braita, you can everybody agrees you can repuncture a hole that
has existed and was just let's say filled up with wax. So
אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel לא שנו
אלא במקום עשוי לשמר. lo shanu ela b'makom asui l'shamer. That's only
if the wax is there to protect it like from the that
it shouldn't get air into it and that it shouldn't get dust
or whatever. אבל לחזק Aval l'chazek if you waxed over a hole
and now the wax is there to strengthen the vessel, it's there
not as a seal to be removed, but it's there to become
part of the vessel now, it's actually like you putty it over
it to now make it part of the vessel, then אסור. assur.
That's forbidden because now this is part of the vessel and making
a hole is like making a new hole. But aren't but isn't
it if it's לחזק l'chazek then if you're making a hole? No,
but the same way before it was you could make it functionally
a functional hole. היכי דמי לשמר היכי דמי לחזק? Heichi dami l'shamer
heichi dami l'chazek? How do we know the difference or what's the
example of the difference? אמר רב חסדא Amar Rav Chisda למעלה מן
היין זהו לשמר. L'ma'ala min hayayin zehu l'shamer. If the hole is
higher than the level of wine then the only reason to seal
it is to protect the contents, not to somehow because the vessel
needs it or the vessel will break or somehow, so it's not
to become part of the vessel. למטה מן היין זהו לחזק L'mata
min hayayin zehu l'chazek if it's below the level of the wine
זהו לחזק zehu l'chazek then it's strengthening because it's preventing the wine
from spilling out, so it's actually doing part of the function of
the vessel and it is becoming part of the vessel, the wax
filler. רבא אמר Rava amar no. למטה מן היין נמי זהו לשמר.
L'mata min hayayin nami zehu l'shamer. That's also לשמר l'shamer because that's
not actually stopping the vessel from breaking, that's just stopping the wine
from going out and therefore that's not enough to make it considered
part of the vessel. היכי דמי לחזק? Heichi dami l'chazek? What does
it really mean to strengthen the vessel? כגון שנקבה למטה מן השמרים.
K'gon she'nikva l'mata min hashamarim. If the wine is at the bottom
on the floor of the vessel there if you don't seal it
up it's going to break because the pressure of the wine coming
out at the hole right there the crack at the bottom will
actually leading it to break because it has the weight of the
wine on top of it, but a crack on the side is
not threatening the integrity of the vessel. Okay, so that's a question
of when you fill something up is it seen as a stopper
and when is it seen as actually becoming part of the vessel.
אמר ליה אביי לרבא Amar lei Abaye l'Rava as Abaye said to
Rava תניא דמסייע לך tanya d'mesaye lach a בריתא Braita a תנא
Tanna that supports you, a בריתא Braita that supports you that you
really need to do something drastic to change the configuration is the
following, this is going to be a little weird analogy, but בית
סתום יש לו ארבע אמות. Bayit satum yesh lo arba amot. You
let's say have sealed off one of the openings of your door.
So when does it stop being considered halachically an opening? I mean
opening of your house, a door, we're talking about like a doorframe.
You sealed it up. When does it stop being considered a doorframe?
What's the relevance? So one relevance is that if you're dividing up
a courtyard everybody gets like a walk in front of their, besides
their equal portion of the courtyard, gets a walk in front of
each one of their doors. Is this still considered a door that
you're entitled to a sidewalk in front of it? That's one issue.
Another issue is, well, so we'll see that's what it starts with.
So בית סתום Bayit satum if the door has been sealed off
יש לו ארבע אמות yesh lo arba amot you still get the
four אמות amot of the sidewalk in front of your door. פרץ
את פצימיו Paratz et ptzimav however if you destroyed the frame the
actual lintel and the doorposts then אין לו ארבע אמות ein lo
arba amot then it stops being considered a door and you don't
get the sidewalk. בית סתום אינו מטמא כל סביביו. Bayit satum eino
metamei kol svivav. Now if you have a dead body in a
house and you seal the door, so when all openings are sealed
it's considered almost like a grave, almost like a mausoleum, and therefore
it means that even if you touch it on the side you're
טמא, tamei, even if you don't go above it, normally טומאה tumah
is only if it goes above, but as long as it hasn't
been sealed all around you would not be טמא tamei by touching
it on the side, only when you got the idea of completely
sealed then it's defined like a grave. So בית סתום אינו מטמא
כל סביביו Bayit satum eino metamei kol svivav if it's just you
have sealed it off it's still not yet מטמא metamei all around
it, only it's still not like a grave. פרץ את פצימיו Paratz
et ptzimav only once you break the doorframe then מטמא כל סביביו
metamei kol svivav then it does. So therefore what does any of
this have to do with anything? So he's saying look what it
shows you is once something has a functional opening it does not
lose that status so quickly.
I mean you can completely seal it off and it's still called
a door.
You have to do something radical. So therefore he says I get
your point Rava that if it's any unless it's sort of working
on the bottom where it's really needed to give a reconfiguration to
the vessel because the vessel was going to break without it then
I would agree, but normal things on the side it would still
be considered an opening and that supports your position. Okay. Now we
go on now that we've talked about making the... openings we talk
about, as Seth said, making actually the spigot. So גובתא, gubsa, what
is the story about making a like גובתא gubsa is a pipe,
a reed, not a reed, whatever, anyway, a tube or pipe that
you're going to stick into the hole? So רב אסר, Rav assar,
Rav says you can't, but שמואל שרי, Shmuel shari, Shmuel says you
can. מחתך לכתחילה, mechatech l'chatchila, to cut actually the pipe to the
right shape, דכולי עלמא לא פליגי דאסר, d'chuli alma lo pligi d'assar,
obviously you can't do that on שבת, Shabbos, that would be like
making it into a vessel, might also be מחתך, mechatech, cutting things
for particular size, דכולי עלמא לא פליגי דאסר, d'chuli alma lo pligi
d'assar, thank you, nobody disagrees that that's forbidden. אהדורי, ahdorei, if the
pipe fell out of the hole, דכולי עלמא לא פליגי דשרי, d'chuli
alma lo pligi d'shari, he says you can put it back in
the hole again, again you're not doing anything new. כי פליגי ki
pligi בחתיכה ולא מתקנא, b'chaticha v'lo misakna, we're talking about the pipe
has been cut, the spigot, but it has not been inserted for
the first time into the hole. מאן דאסר, man d'assar, the one
that says it's forbidden, גזרינן דילמא אתי למחתך לכתחילה, gazrinan dilma ati
l'michtach l'chatchila, notice, doesn't say that putting a pipe in a hole
is making a vessel, okay? Because that's not changing the physical nature
of the vessel, it's something that could easily be removed, so that's
actually not making a vessel. The worst concern is if we let
you do that, next time you'll come to cut the pipe and
do it לכתחילה. l'chatchila. ומאן דשרי, u'man d'shari, the one who permits,
לא גזרינן, lo gazrinan, says we don't make that גזירה. gezeira. כתנאי,
ke'tanai, this is like a debate of תנאים. tannaim. אין חותכין שפופרת
ביום טוב ein chotchin shififerta b'Yom Tov ואין צריך לומר בשבת, v'ein
tzarich lomar b'Shabbos, you cannot cut again like a tube, a pipe
on יום טוב Yom Tov and certainly not on שבת.
Shabbos. נפלה, nafla, if it falls down, it has to be taken
out, you'll see, מחזירין אותו בשבת ואין צריך לומר ביום טוב, machzirin
oto b'Shabbos v'ein tzarich lomar b'Yom Tov, you can put it back
in on שבת Shabbos and certainly on יום טוב. Yom Tov. רבי
יאשיה מיקל, Rabbi Yoshi meikel, Rabbi Yoshi is lenient quite a bit,
that's quite fascinating. Now where do we ever have that phrase מיקל?
meikel? Like it doesn't actually say he permits, it just sort of
talks about he's lenient. Anyway, he's מיקל. meikel. רבי יאשיה האי, Rabbi
Yoshi hai,
which case is Rabbi Yoshi going on? אילימא רישא, ilema reisha, the
first
case about cutting the actual pipe, הא קמתקן מנא, ha kamisaken mana,
you're fixing it, you're making a vessel! אלא אסיפא, ella aseifa, the
end, putting it back, תנא קמא נמי מחזר, Tanna Kamma nami machzer,
so everyone lets you put it back. אלא, ella, it must be
that the issue is a case not being discussed, בחתיכה ולא מתקנא,
b'chaticha v'lo misakna, it's cut and it hasn't been put in, איכא
בינייהו, hika beinaihu, מר סבר גזרינן, mar savar gazrinan, one says we
make a גזירה, gezeira, ומר סבר לא גזרינן, u'mar savar lo gazrinan,
we do not. דרש רב ששת בריה דרב אידי משמיה דרב יוחנן
הלכה כרבי יאשיה, darash Rav Sheshet brei d'Rav Idi mishmei d'Rav Yochanan
halacha k'Rabbi Yoshi, we
actually allow you to put it in. So again, what we have
found out so far on the עמוד ב amud bet is a
few leniencies. The עמוד א amud aleph is where the stringencies, and
the עמוד ב amud bet is the leniencies. So if you've already
got the hole and it's sealed off, you can remove the wax,
you can puncture the seal, if it was already a vessel and
then it was sealed, and that translates into a lot of these
discussions around cans nowadays, that they're already a vessel and then they're
just sealed. But then the question becomes, when does it change the
configuration? When they put the top on my tuna fish can, right?
Is that like the wax seal in a hole, or is that
like לחזק, l'chazek, that really does permanently change the configuration until I,
that stuff will last for a century. So is that really just
לשמר? l'shamer? But maybe that's just to do a good job of
לשמר. l'shamer. So anyway, but that's very important in the question of
when it was a vessel and now it's been somehow changed, when
does it, can you just remove that additional thing that was added?
That's the wax issue. And then this issue, which is less relevant,
which is something when you're adding something to make it functional, you're
putting the pipe in, the straw in, but you're not really changing
the physical configuration of the thing itself, that clearly is permissible. One
minute, Charlie. But on that, how long wine bottles with corks also
can last for centuries. And there, I knew someone who had some
2,000-year-old wine. Oh my god, did it turn into vinegar? You wouldn't
want to drink it. Okay, fine, not. Anyway, so that is exactly
these questions about things like the tuna fish cans, is that basically
just לשמר? l'shamer? So that's really what it's been doing, לשמר, l'shamer,
it's just there to protect the tuna fish from going bad, I
guess. Like in a jar of olives when you turn it. Right,
right, that's okay, that's not, yeah, yeah, I mean, you're using it
but you're not, you're using the jar as it were but you're
not changing anything. So is this the issue, if we're talking about
above or on the side, which was that מחלוקת? machlokes? Right, that
was that מחלוקת. machlokes. And then does anyone say that like since
we're not making chicken coops anymore, like this whole thing is. No,
nobody said that. Okay, מימסין כוורת, meim'sin kiva, now we move on.
I'll go back and say a few more things about the packaging
after we finish the דף. daf. Now we go on to putting
the wax on, and that's about ממרח, memareiach, and as I talked
to you, mentioned you, how does that apply to things like Vaseline
and Aquaphor and those types of issues? But here, you're spreading wax
to really make it make the wax function in its spread state,
whereas in most of the cases nowadays that come up about ממרח
memareiach is more about just applying it all around. Here it's really
to make it function as the smooth surface thing. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says משחא, mishcha, if you're dealing with משחא, mishcha, which
apparently is a very thick oil, רב אסר ושמואל שרי. Rav assar
u'Shmuel shari. Rav forbids it and Shmuel says it's permissible. מאן דאסר,
Man d'assur, the one that forbids it, גזרינן משום שעוה, gazarinan mishum
shaava, that if we allow that, you will come to allow you
to use wax. ומאן דשרי, U'man d'shari, and the one that allows
it, לא גזרינן, lo gazarinan, we're not גוזר, gozer, so apparently maybe
you know you could put some oil on and would create some
type of a seal as well, but if we let you do
that, will you come to do wax? אמר ליה רב שמואל בר
רב חנא לרב יוסף, Amar lei Rav Shmuel bar Rav Chana l'Rav
Yosef, פירושא אמרת לן משמיה דרב משחא שרי. peirusha amrat lan mishmei
d'Rav mishcha shari. So he said to רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, you
explicitly told us, here we started by saying that רב Rav said
אסור, assur, he said you told us in the name of רב
Rav that it was permissible. Okay. אמר דביתהו דרב יוסף אמר שמואל,
Amar d'veiteihu d'Rav Yosef amar Shmuel, טרפא דאסא דאסר אסר. tarpa d'assa
d'assur assur. A leaf of a myrtle leaf is forbidden. Now what
does it mean? They would take a myrtle leaf and use it
as a type of a pipe in the bar- in the side
of the barrel. So they would basically fold it over, you know,
fold it and stick it in the barrel and it would be
used to just, you know, to draw the wine out. So that's
forbidden to do that. מאי טעמא, Mai taama, why? I mean we
just discussed putting a pipe into a barrel. So, רב יימר מדפתי
אמר גזירה משום מרזב, Rav Yeimar mi-Difti amar gezeira mishum marzev, because
if we allow that, we're going to allow you to come to
do a whole like... what's it called? Yeah, pipe, but what's... what's
the thing that takes rain off of your... spout, spigot, gutter. Okay,
anyway, anyway, somehow it's going to be, we're afraid that that will
lead to you to make something much more radical. Now, you know,
take a look, תוספות Tosafot says משום מרזב, mishum marzev, תוספות Tosafot
פירש הר"י, peraysh ha-Ri, שלא יבא ליתן על גגו מרזב, shelo yavo
liteit al gago marzev, not somehow because you know, we just said
that you can put a pipe back in, so why should a
leaf be any different? Okay, and he says that וקשיא דבגופסא נמי
נגזר, v'kashya d'begufsa nami nigzar, how about putting the pipe in the
barrel, we said that was allowed? אלא נראה לרבי כפירוש הקונטרס, Ela
nira l'Rabbi k'perush ha-kuntres, שלא יתקן מרזב ליינו, shelo yetakein marzev l'yeino,
שיפול היין בתוכו וילך למרחוק. sheyipol hayayin b'tocho v'yeilech l'merachok. Now, why
is this different than the... this is great, why is it different
than the pipe we just said was okay? So he says, דכי
שקיל עליא דהדס ומכפלו כעין מרזב, d'ki shakil alya d'hadas u-machpelo k'ein
marzev, because here you're actually making its functionality. It's not a pre-existing
pipe that you're just sticking in. You're folding the leaf into serving
as a pipe. So נראה כעושה מרזב, nira k'oseh marzev, that's like
you are now making a whole, you know, a whole funnel, not
a funnel, a whole whatever pipe. אבל בגופסא, Aval begufsa, by the
straw, שאינו עושה בו שום מעשה, she-eino oseh bo shum maaseh, you
just stick it in, לא גזרינן. lo gazarinan. Okay, so that's the
concern. Somehow here this is worse than the straw because you're actually
folding the leaf and creating it now functionally as a pipe. And
therefore one says it's not allowed. מאי טעמא? Mai taama? רב יימר
Rav Yeimar משום מרזב. mishum marzev. רב אשי Rav Ashi אמר לא,
גזירה שמא יקטום, amar lo, gezeira shema yiktom, we're afraid that you'll
come to cut it off of a branch. רש"י Rashi for some
reason says not a branch that's growing, even a branch that's not
growing, but still we don't want you cutting it off. Okay, and
because that's somehow like fixing it. Now you've like... it's not exactly
clear what are you fixing, the branch, the leaf, but maybe if
that's how you're going to use the leaf, it's like making some
vessel. מאי בינייהו, Mai beinaihu, what's the difference? איכא בינייהו דקטים ומנח.
Icha beinaihu d'katim u-manach. So the... that the leaf is already cut.
You have a free leaf, you know, of a... of a myrtle.
Can you fold it and use it as a spigot? Okay, now
בי סדיא. bei sadya. Now we're just going to do a couple
of debates of רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel that have nothing to
do with the earlier discussion. Okay, so this is basically like a
type of a blanket that you can like fold and, you know,
use as a blanket, use as a pillow, but you want to
get it out to you in the middle of the street and
you're not allowed to carry. So do you- can you wrap yourself
with it and use it like clothing until you get it to
the street where you want it and then undo it and use
it as a pillow? רב אסר ושמואל שרי. Rav assur v'Shmuel shari.
רב Rav says no and שמואל Shmuel says yes. ברכין, B'rachin, if
it's soft, דכולי עלמא לא פליגי דשרי, d'kulei alma lo pligi d'shari,
everybody says it's allowed because that would be a normal thing to
be wearing and therefore it could be considered clothing when you're wearing
it. ובקשין, U-vekashin, if it's... if it's very stiff, דכולי עלמא לא
פליגי דאסור, d'kulei alma lo pligi d'assur, nobody would disagree that it's
forbidden because that would never... doesn't really function as clothing. כי פליגי
במצעי, Ki pligi b'mitzai, they're arguing by, you know, it's medium grade
between soft and... and stiff. By the way, the structure here is
not only to the debate of רב Rav and שמואל, Shmuel, but
a debate of רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel that's being qualified. This
extreme everybody agrees, that extreme everybody agrees, they're only arguing in the
middle case. מאן דאסר מחזי כמשאוי, Man d'assur mechzi k'masoi, the one
that says it's forbidden says even if technically it- it constitutes clothing
when you're wearing it, it looks like a burden, it looks like
you're just, you know, doing this to carry it, which is why
you are doing it, but it actually even looks that way. ומאן
דשרי לא מחזי כמשאוי. U-man d'shari lo mechzi k'masoi. No, it doesn't
look that way; as long as you're wearing it, it looks like
clothing. והא דרב לאו בפירוש איתמר אלא מכללא איתמר. V'ha d'Rav lav
b'feirush itmar ela miklala itmar. The fact that רב Rav said it's
a problem was not said explicitly but it was inferred. דרב איקלע
לההוא אתרא דלא הוה ליה ריוחא. D'Rav ikla l'hahu atra d'lo hava
lei rivcha. רב Rav went to a place that there was not
enough space for people to sit. נפק יתיב בכרמלית, Nafak yatib b'karmelit,
so he went down and he sat in the, you know, in
the yard, the כרמלית. karmelit. אייתו ליה בי צדיתא, Aisu lei bei
tzadiso, so they figured it was look, it's terrible, רב Rav is
sitting out there, he has to sit on the ground, so they
brought him this type of blanket by wearing it out there to
him. לא יתיב, Lo yasiv, he refused to sit on it. מן
דחזא סבר משום דבי צדיתא אסור, Man dechaza sabar mishum de-bisaya assur,
the one who saw it assumed that it was because, you know,
he ruled that it's not allowed to wear a blanket out for,
you know, as a way of getting it to where you need
it. ולאו היא, V'lohi, but that wasn't why, actually it's not true,
that wasn't why he didn't do it and רב Rav really doesn't
think it's a problem. So דרב אכרוזי מכריז, de-Rav achruzei machriz, because
רב Rav actually had announced בי צדיתא שרי, bisaya sharei, that actually
it's permissible to wear, to wear this blanket to get it to
where you need it. So why didn't he sit on it? ומשום
כבוד רבותינו לא ישב עליו, Umishum kvod raboseinu lo yashav alav, because
with him were other rabbis and they weren't bringing out the blankets
for the other rabbis, they were only bringing out the blanket for
רב. Rav. So he did not want to sit on this blanket
if the other rabbis were not being treated the same way. ומאן
אינהו, Uman inu, and who were these other rabbis? רב כהנא ורב
אסי. Rav Kahana v'Rav Assi. Okay, so that's a nice little end
to that discussion. Let's read, I want to read a little bit
further, get to the bottom of the דף, daf, and then hopefully
as I say a minute or two back more about the about
the packages. נותנין תבשיל לתוך הבור בשביל שיהא שמור, Nosnin tavshil l'soch
habor bishvil sheyehei shamur, you can lower like your your stew, your
your food into a pit, an empty pit, you know, because it's
cool down at the bottom of the pit. So it's a type
of a refrigerator in order to protect it, to keep it cool.
ואת המים היפים ברעים, V'es hamayim hayafim b'ra'im, and you can also
take like a jug of, you know, of good water and, you
know, submerge it in in bad water, polluted water, but as בשביל
שיצננו, bishvil sheyitznanu, because as again, as a type of a refrigerator
to keep it cool. Why would you want bad water? No, meaning,
oh, or to get it hot. Yeah, but if it's not going
to get, yeah. And that's the next line. ואת הצונן בחמה, V'es
hatzonin b'chama, you can put cold things in the sun בשביל שיחמו,
bishvil sheyeichamu, that it should heat up. Of course, when you're talking
about heating up, you get a question how hot is it going
to get, and is it going to be בישול? bishul? In the
sun, it's not a problem. Okay, because there's no בישול חמה. bishul
chama. מי שנשרו כליו בדרך, Mi shenishru kelav baderech, so all of
that is still food. Now we get onto, we're leaving food into
a new area. So until now the whole פרק's perek been about
food. New story. מי שנשרו כליו בדרך Mi shenishru kelav baderech במים,
b'mayim, if your if your clothes got soaked in water when you
were walking, maybe because you walked through a river, maybe it rained,
there's a little debate if it matters which of those two תוספות
Tosfos discusses it. Anyway, מהלך בהן ואינו חושש, Mehalach bahen v'eino choshesh,
you can walk with them, you don't have to be concerned. Concerned
maybe about incidental squeezing is an issue or concern that that people
will look, think that you've done laundry. I mean, you're wearing wet
clothing. הגיע לחצר החיצונה, Higia l'chatzer hachitzona, when you get to your
outer courtyard and now you want to take them off because who
wants to be wearing wet clothing, but now you're in a רשות
היחיד, reshus hayachid, your courtyard, then שוטחן בחמה, shotchan bachama, you can
spread them out in the sun to dry, אבל לא כנגד העם,
aval lo kineged ha'am, not in front of people, because people will
think you've done your laundry. So the question is, but if it's
a concern about מראית העין, maris ayin, שטחן בחדרי חדרים, sheta b'chadrei
chadarim, so the גמרא's Gemara going to ask that, that'll be tomorrow.
Okay, so tomorrow we'll deal with the last case. Let's just do
the little גמרא Gemara on the first cases. פשיטא, Pshita, obviously you
can put stuff in the bottom of a pit. No, מהו דתימא
נגזר משום אשויי גומות, mahu d'seima nigzar mishum ashvuyei gumos, maybe if
we let you put it in the pit you'll come to smooth
out the bottom of the pit, קא משמע לן, kamashma lan, we're
not concerned. ואת המים היפים ברעים, V'es hamayim hayafim b'ra'im, the good
water in the bad water, פשיטא, pshita, that's also obvious. סיפא איצטריכא
ליה, Seifa itztaricha lei, you need it for the last case. ואת
הצונן בחמה, V'es hatzonin b'chama, the cold stuff in the sun, הא
נמי פשיטא, hani pshita, that's also obvious. No, מהו דתימא נגזר דילמא
אתי לטמוני ברמץ, mahu d'seima nigzar dilma asi litmoni b'remetz, if we
let you put it in the sun, then you'll come to put
stuff in, in, you know, in ashes, and we don't let you
do הטמנה hatmana in ashes because you'll come to stir the ashes.
So קא משמע לן kamashma lan that we are not concerned with
that. Okay, so anyway, so, so okay, so we'll continue with the
issue about the clothes. I'll just say the last thing about packages
is just to like remind you what we said about packages. So
on the at the end we had a whole focus on the
type of hole you're making. At the beginning that was not the
focus at all. And the גמרא Gemara distinguished between are you trying
to make it into a פתח, pesach, are you trying, or are
you trying to make it look nice? And distinguished between you know
where you, you know where it was located, on the top, on
the side and so on. Certainly it had cases where get getting
access to it wasn't a problem, destroying the packaging around the figs,
cutting off the top of the barrel, right, making a hole in
the top of the of the cork. It certainly had cases where
things were allowed. The cases where it wasn't allowed were things where
it was like on the side and it was done in a
and there was an issue that you were doing it in order
to be like a פתח, pesach, to be an opening. So is
that specifically about functionality? Is that about the discussion at the end
that there's certain definitions of holes and therefore it's very much within
this narrow definition of a hole? That's not clear. And the big
question for us becomes you know, whatever, all of you know these
issues about like you know, again, I think that always a good
example is making the the spigot in the in the the old
fashioned milk cartons, right? Is that just like a convenient way to
get it or no, yeah, it makes it very functional? Or do
you say well actually you know it had that functionality before, it
was just sealed off similarly to the case about the filling it
with the wax. So you know the exact parameters are not clear.
The fact that nowadays most of our things are disposable makes it
a lot more lenient of course according to many it makes almost
everything allowed and you know some don't go that far. Also the
fact that according to some all these issues here are rabbinic. Certainly
the גמרא Gemara by the bottom seems to think the whole issue
was rabbinic and some think that all these issues are rabbinic because
it's not really making something so that also is a side to
be lenient. All of that being said you know I'm pretty strict.
Actually Dara and I have different practices because I will open up
tuna fish cans halfway I won't open up the whole way and
then scoop them out but I won't open up soda tops and
she does the reverse so somehow it works out. It's like Jack
Sprat's wife. You're gonna live longer. Okay but anyway you can see
why these issues are so complicated because the question becomes do you
start to focus on defining the whole or do you start focusing
on defining you know is it making it like a functional and
then how you draw the line between I'm just trying to get
it to the contents versus I want to make it functional like
when you open up a potato chip bag at the top you're
not doing it because you know it's just doing because it's less
messy than and it's easier than you know than trying to cut
it in the side and get to it that way but on
the other hand you know it does give it a certain amount
of functionality. So how much is that considered functionality if its primary
use is just to get the stuff out you know? Again these
are the issues that come up. This is the primary סוגיא Sugya
for it but now you see why there's just so many. And
what do you do you know those things that have a ziplock
thing but you gotta rip off the top first? That is a
bigger problem. The things that are specifically made that after you open
it to be resealable and reusable you know those are definitely bigger
problems than the rest. Is it אסור? Asur?